<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Engagement vindicated; from all the objections, cavils, scruples, that wilfull opposers, or doubtfull, unresolved judgements may cast upon it. Wherein, all such objections are answered; the government proved; the Engagement it self both lawful, and necessary, from clearest principles of conscience and reason. To the satisfaction of all such as are doubting. / By T.B.</title>
            <author>T. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76368</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B182</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E589_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206305</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865478</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865478</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117721</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76368)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117721)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 90:E589[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Engagement vindicated; from all the objections, cavils, scruples, that wilfull opposers, or doubtfull, unresolved judgements may cast upon it. Wherein, all such objections are answered; the government proved; the Engagement it self both lawful, and necessary, from clearest principles of conscience and reason. To the satisfaction of all such as are doubting. / By T.B.</title>
                  <author>T. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Mab and A. Coles for T.B. and are sold at the sign of the Angel in Corn-hil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "Jan: 7th 1649"; the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117721:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> ENGAGEMENT <hi>VINDICATED;</hi> From all the Objections, Cavils, Scruples, that wilfull Oppoſers, or doubtfull, unreſolved Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may caſt upon it. <hi>WHEREIN,</hi> All ſuch OBJECTIONS are anſwered; The GOVERNMENT proved; The ENGAGEMENT it ſelf both lawful, and neceſſary, from cleareſt Principles of Conſcience and Reaſon. <hi>To the ſatiſfaction of all ſuch as are doubting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> T. B.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Mab</hi> and <hi>A. Coles</hi> for <hi>T. B.</hi> and are ſold at the ſign of the Angel in Corn-hil. 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:117721:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117721:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THe great obligation and ſoveraign commands of a Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in all its dictates, though proceeding from an erroneous principle, yea though they are the offſpring of a Conſcience unreſolved or miſſed; have allured me into the writing ſomething for the ſatisfaction of men in this uncertainty, (which like a <hi>fluctus decumanus</hi> invades them, and totters all their motions.) So that they who are willing to take Reaſon along with them as a guide, and proportion their actions to it as a rule, may hence be ſatisfied in their ſcrupuloſities, and with a full mind ſet their hands to this Subſcription; which is ſo neceſſary a policie, that it is impoſſible for the Kingdome or State to continue it ſelf in this New-Model, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, or ſomething of a like ſtamp or ſtrain.</p>
            <p>'Its true indeed, a man is to obey conſcience; and rebellion againſt its poſitions and canons, though erroneous, is unlawfull; yet no man muſt blind himſelf, as it were, &amp; ſtop out that light that might better inform him, and change the verdict of conſcience. I hope ſome light will ſlow into mens mindes from the enſuing Treatiſe; the very deſign of which, is neither baſely and paraſitically to flatter the great Movers and Wheeles of this action in their proceedings, nor ſervilely to comply with a by-opinion; but out of an ingenuous aime at the ſatisfaction of men yet unreſolved, and the further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of thoſe who have entertained this Subſcription into their engagements. And here I cannot but take up a complaint and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel againſt thoſe, who endeavour to lay ſnares in mens way, and further to entangle them in their actions, by crying up I know not what unneceſſary cavils, and eaſting dirt upon the actions of the Propounders, making an advantage againſt the Thing it ſelfe, from the Authours of it, and taking riſt to declaim againſt the Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe (forſooth) the Setters on foot and Motioners of it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117721:3"/>are obnoxious to ſuch and ſuch exceptions: Whereas if they dealt impartially, the Thing it ſelf is to be conſidered; elſe, we muſt refuſe many Commodities, becauſe they ſlow from ill Authors. Others will needs make friends fall out with one another, and which is as bad, force Subordinates to mutinie, againſt that commonly received rule, <hi>Subordinata non pugnant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But not to pervert this into a Satyrical invective, I ſeriouſly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe all to part with their ſeverall intereſts and biaſſes of affection, and nakedly to embrace the right and equity of things, and accept of this Diſcourſe as a ſervant to <hi>praeferre facem,</hi> and carry the candle before them. Which is the attempt of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A well-wiſher to peace and unity both in Church and State, T. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117721:3"/>
            <head>The Engagement Vindicated, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He great Bodies Politick of States and Kingdoms, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go the moſt viſible and eminent, though not the moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent viciſſitudes. Every change of theſe is gaz'd upon as a ſignal act of Providence, firing a Beacon as it were, to rouze the World into wonder and obſervation: For every State and Republique or Kingdom interweaving their ſeveral intereſts, and linking one with another, the tranſmutation of one is the concernment of all. That there are ſuch variations, who that is leaſt acquainted with the world doth not now perceive; our Age having been ſpectatour of a very memorable one: And Hiſtories will acquaint us with many other, not onely with the riſing or falling of the States themſelves, but with a mutation of the Government and adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them. For as it hath been obſerved, there is a threefold change in every State; a Riſe, or increaſe; an Acme, or top; a Fall, or total de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay: We may note the ſame in Governments, which as well as other things have their Climactericks, and Criticiſmes of time. This Kingdom hath been often bandied by ſuch changes; and every ſuch change begets new principles, and Axiomes of State-Policy; ſo that thoſe, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly hit the former, are quite out-dated and worth nothing in the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive: For as I ſaid before, though ſuch viciſſitudes are not frequent, the great Wheele of Providence not often overturning theſe; but the Preparatives to them working ſlowly and inſenſibly, retard the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of them; and the grand diſturbance and diſcompoſure which neceſſarily accompanies, not ſuiting with that order, God in whoſe hand the Ballances are, delights in; yet they are ſo far different, when they come, from that which was before them, that they new-mould the ſubjects of then: and though many of the neceſſary Laws that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the former as a government, and not as ſuch a government; yet many muſt needs be expunged and wip'd out of the Canon, as diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trically oppoſite.</p>
            <p>For the better confirming the new diſpenſation of a metamorphos'd Kingdome, Oathes and Engagements have been alwayes held effectuall,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117721:4"/>and practiſed as conducing; to which how farre a man may lawfully yield, is the queſtion now on the rack, and to which I immediately ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe my ſelf.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſquare out my diſcourſe by theſe diſquiſitions,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Concerning Oaths and other ingagements.</item>
               <item>2. Concerning Government.</item>
               <item>3. Concerning this Subſcription.</item>
               <item>4. Concerning this Government.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Oathes are the ſtricteſt Tyes and Obligations, that a man can be under; for they directly reſpect and atteſt God the revenger of perjury, and conſcience is ſpecially bound by it.</p>
            <p>An Oath then is the confirmation of any thing atteſted, or promiſed, by the invocation of God; and ſo a ſpecial Engagement to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of a promiſe, and the upright atteſtation of any thing affirmed, concerning which, we hold theſe three concluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Oathes are lawful under the Goſpel, for they depended not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Ceremonial Right or Judicial Conſtitution, but are purely of a Moral complexion; and ſo not diſcharg'd Chriſtendom, under any notion of a Ceremony out-dated, or a Judicial Rite now out-cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; nor can any reaſon be given of the ancient Inſtitution, and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of them, which doth not exactly compromiſe with the uſe of it under the Goſpel. They much miſtake, who conclude otherwiſe out of Chriſts, <hi>Sweare not at all;</hi> which muſt either be underſtood of the neighbour-formes of ſwearing, or the vain and familiar cuſtome of idle Oathes, for which it is to be feared the Land now mourns: True it is, to ſweare by any thing beneath God, is not onely meerly unlawful, but comprehends in it a degree of idolatry; for none can be a ſufficient witneſſe of an Oath, but the Searcher of hearts; but to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſter God, as it were, of this part of his Worſhip, ſeems ſacrilegious, and there we may to ſuch a one, Thou that abhorreſt Idols, doeſt thou commit Sacriledge?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Oathes are to be taken conformable to the fence and meaning of the giver, and not under thoſe by and underhand meanings, which we reſerve to our ſelves; for if ſo, an Oath is a meer piece of mockery, and to no purpoſe; for the adaequate end of it being ſome obligation propos'd, if we yet take it, and find reaſons from the Obligation of it, the end and aime of it is clearly fruſtrate and diſappointed: Yea, the Obligation of an Oath ſpecially reſpecting the conſcience, and binding the inward man as well as the outward, 'tis neceſſary to the taking of an Oath, that the heart ſhould as fully and freely comply with the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and matter of it, as the outward.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:117721:4"/>
3. Oathes may be impos'd by a lawfull Magiſtrate, without domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering or lording over the conſcience, provided it be in a caſe not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the law of God, for all muſt be ſubject to that royall law: But the great knot of this controverſie lies in this, That which ſeems to one conſcience to be according to Gods law, ſeems to another quite contrary; and what muſt the unſatisfied conſcience doe? To which I anſwer,</p>
            <p>The conſcience may be in moſt points clearly ſatisfied, if it be not wilfull; but if it ſtill ſtand out, and deny it ſelfe ſatisfied, the man ſo conſcienc'd is to reſolve upon ſuffering. But the Magiſtracy is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour all meanes to find out the native principle of reſiſtance, and if it prove truly tenderneſſe of conſcience, the diſcretion of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is expected in patience, and a totall forbearance, if in things not indifferent: But if after cleere repreſentations of the lawfulneſſe of the thing, the man ſtill holds his firſt principle of reſiſtance, and it be in a matter not indifferent, the penalty muſt be proportion'd, not onely to the offence, but the perſon; For a ſcrupulous conſcience is a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, at leaſt, a tryall of God's upon a man.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A Magiſtrate lawfully conſtituted can take off the obligation of an oath, if he be <hi>in materia ſuperior,</hi> if the matter of it be in his power; as a man ſwearing fealty to a Prince, may by the diſpenſation of the Prince, lay downe this obligation: If it be in matter of Religion, or ſuch caſes, it is beyond the reach of his power; nay, hee cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>engage him of that obligation knit between him and another. It is a high arrogancy of the Pope, that uſurpes ſo ſupreme a Prerogative.</p>
            <p n="5">5. When the <hi>ratio formalis,</hi> the formality of the oath ceaſeth, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation ceaſeth too. As a man ſwearing homage and obedience to a Prince or Lord, his obligation ceaſeth, when he is unlorded or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>princ'd, becauſe he was bound to him onely under that capacity, which ceaſing, the obligation muſt needs ceaſe too.</p>
            <p>The ſecond inquiry is concerning Government, which is a ſubjection of men to the obedience of lawes, and the Makers, Keepers, Officers of thoſe lawes; whether he be onely one, and ſo is called Monarchy; or by a few of the chiefe, and ſo Ariſtocracy; or by the Repreſentatives of a people, and ſo a Democracy. Concerning Government, I lay downe theſe following concluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A government is eſtabliſhed by the law of nature, without go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment a ſecond Chaos muſt needs returne upon the world: This on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maintaines it a Coſmos, cements and joints it, that it ſtands and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines a body; every confuſion is deſtructive; but great bodies, twiſted by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117721:5"/>many ſeverals, muſt needs preſently ruinate and diſſolve, if unknit by the want of goverment. Now nature being a principle of ſelfe-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, not onely leads men to this conſtitution, but enſtamps upon Governours ſuch an impreſſe of Majeſty, that it even commands the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hearts of men ſubjected to them. Lawes, and Governours the tutelar Angels of them, have been by all States and Politicians lookt upon as the very Baſiſes of the world, from which if it be unhing'd, it muſt needs ſink into a heap of rubbiſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The firſt Government came in neither by Election nor Conqueſt, but by the right of Primogeniture. Heires or families were heires of Kingdomes, and had the power of life and death; and ſo long then were the lives of men continued to them, that they might ſee a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Kingdome riſing out of their families; their childrens children, and ſervants children, all members of the family, and ſubject to the firſt-borne.</p>
            <p n="3">3. No other government is individually a conſtitution of the law of nature; for if it were, they muſt needs offer force to nature, that are not moulded under ſuch a government. But wee know the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> under Gods ſpeciall adminiſtration, were ſubject to diverſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments, and that with Gods approbation. Nature hath not pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually oblig'd men to any individuall or particular Form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but only generally impreſs'd the notion of Government upon men, yea, and beaſts too, at leaſt a reſemblance of it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A Republique comes neareſt to the law of nature, ſince the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding of men from that family-government, which was the neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſequent of their abridg'd lives. It was the ambition of ſome ſtirring heads, that firſt ſcrewed them into thrones; but the very di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctate of nature ſeems to point men to the other, unleſſe ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar emergent give ſome one a particular, though but temporary reigne.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Monarchs are meerly Creatures of the Peoples choiſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent upon the continuation of their pleaſure. I do not mean the hurly-burly confuſions of the people, but of the orderly choſen Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives of a people; and it can be no treaſon, or breach of law, to proceed againſt them either to a depoſall, or upon forfeiture of their truſt, to further puniſhment. For if they came in by conqueſt, the people arm'd with opportunity may lawfully regaine their liberty; if they are meerly elective, the known axiome ſhall ſpeak, <hi>Cujus eſt inſtitue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ejus eſt deſtituere;</hi> if by both, yea, and confirm'd by ſucceſſion, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements of Parliaments, and particular Subjects, yet they are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117721:5"/>accountable to theſe Creators of them, which may ſtrip them of their authority, and diſoblige themſelves, if it be done by a generall conſent; for if any particular man, or company of men attempt it, not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by orderly procedure, they are ſo long Traitors, Uſurpers, Rebels, and liable to the penalties of them, as long as their actions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main unback'd, unauthoriz'd, and diſcountenanc'd by the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives of that State, who are jointly the onely competent actors, and moſt juſtly enabled to negotiate Publique affaires. And though 'tis true, Monarchy doth moſt reſemble Gods manner of government; yet this doth not prove it the moſt accommodate to humane affaires, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we could attaine to a ſucceſſion of Kings perpetually, that would exactly imitate God in his diſpenſation. For the height and unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted power of Kings layes them open to the ſtrongeſt provocations and temptations to Tyranny, and facilitates to them the deſtruction of that Kingdome they are ordained the defenders of; for I cannot conceive of them as other than Officers of the Kingdome, choſen to the higheſt Province and charge by the People; or elſe, who have cut their way to the Throne by the ſword; whom the next opportunity may as lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dethrone and diſ-impower.</p>
            <p>Three objections impugne theſe Premiſes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We read of no ſuch power in Scripture inſtituted on the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but rather the contrary. To omit ſome footſteps that may be found of it, we will concede; but yet the caſe is farre different, for we read of God's ſpeciall acting in the promotion of thoſe to the Throne, which we can no otherwiſe gheſſe of now, than by the hand of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which permits of many things it doth not approve of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. God attributes to himſelfe in ſpeciall the dealing with and ordering of Kings, ſetting them up, turning their hearts, entitling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe King of Kings. I anſwer, we may find as many eminent expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of others, meaner Officers, as of them. But let that be granted; God herein condeſcends, as in many other places, to the cuſtomes of men, amongſt whom Princes are look'd upon generally as the moſt abſolute and ſupreme, &amp; ſo it is <hi>argumentum à majori;</hi> if God ſwayes their Scepters, and hath them at his direction, much the more, ſublunary men of the world, that move in a lower ſphere: He muſt be a great King, that is King of Kings, who diſpoſes of the Kings and Kingdomes of the world.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, They object the Example of primitive Times, who found neck for any yoak, and back for any ſufferings, that they might not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice the Royal Prerogative, or prove in the leaſt commotioners of States. But I anſwer, let it firſt be pro'vd, that there were ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117721:6"/>numbers of Chriſtians, as might make up and be orderly cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the Repreſentatives of a Kingdome: and then we have yet a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and a full anſwer to their objection, <hi>viz.</hi> In thoſe times, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God ſo directing it, the ſufferings of the Chriſtians were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd to the advantage of the Church, according to that receiv'd Axiome, <hi>Sanguis martirum fuit ſemen Eccleſiae,</hi> The Churches harveſt was rooted in the Martyrs blood. And ſo eager were men on propagating the Church this way, that many doubt, whether they were not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, and with good intentions, profuſe and prodigal of themſelves by their over-liberal ſufferings.</p>
            <p>I come now to ſpeak of the third propoſal for Inquiry.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Concering this Subſcription; and firſt briefly, as I promiſed, of the nature of Engagements. Engagements are of an order inferior to Oaths, not atteſting God, not immediately eyeing Religion and Conſcience; but obligatory by the law of mutual Faith and Honeſty, the Pillar of humane Converſe. So that a man may with leſſe regret give up himſelf to ſuch a tye, and the Magiſtrate with greater authority exact it; Not that I would hereby prejudice the Civil-world, by introducing an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obliging principle, to the Faith promiſed and oblig'd by Engagement, or open a back-door and evaſion to diſhoneſty; for though ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes imply conditions, yet I conceive Engagements and Promiſes of this nature, as ſtrict in this reſpect as Oaths, that a man is to eye all inconveniences, and not after the ſubmiſſion to the Engagement make inquiry; but their Obligation differs in regard of the witneſſe of our Engagement, God being concern'd immediately in one, man imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately in the other; and in regard of the principle engag'd, in one Conſcience and Religion, in the other Moral Honeſty and Faith; ſo that the latter bears not the face of dominion over Conſcience, as the other doth, and ſo with more right may be impos'd by the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. But particularly, This Engagement is of the ſame nature, juſtly impos'd by the Civil Magiſtrate, juſtly may the neglect of it be puniſh'd by him according to his arbitrement, becauſe the refuſal cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt with the good of the Common-wealth. The reſt of the time will be well ſpent in the removal of Objections: And firſt,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is oppoſite and contradictory to Oaths, Engagements of a higher nature, yea to a Solemn Covenant. For the firſt, we grant it is ſo: But we anſwer, the Obligation of thoſe Oaths, is already ceas'd; for, the formality of the Obligation is null'd: As, we were bound to the maintaining of the King and his Heirs; but they being wholly annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, the Obligation muſt of neceſſity ceaſe, as we prov'd heretofore.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117721:6"/>They were Kings, by the common conſent of the People, which hath dethron'd them; ſo that we are wholly diſengaged and free.</p>
            <p>For the Covenant, I anſwer, it is not contrary to that, contending onely for that Government which is ſuitable to the law of God and Reaſon, with both which this Law is exactly correſpondent, which we have pro'vd before.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It contradicts the former agreeances of themſelves, the <hi>Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the People,</hi> and the like; an Argument much preſt in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique auditory, though ſomething unſuitable to an exerciſe proper to practical Divinity. That which was concluded by ſome Pieces or Parts of the Kingdom, doth not reflect on the whole; or, was it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the Body or Repreſentatives of it, yet it was not matur'd nor ratified, and ſo not engaging to non-alteration: Beſides, I do not conceive of this Government, as a thing unalterable; nor this En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, as ſuch as for ever to diſoblige us to any other; but onely thus far it binds, to reſtrain the irregular motions or inſurrections of any not lawfully called to it, and obliging to the confirmation of this, till altered by due courſe of law. So that if the Repreſentatives, and Pillars of this Government, ſhould now on the ſudden face about, and revive the ancient Monarchy, we were not at all bound to the ſupport of this, by this Engagement: for ſo long I account any Government unlawful, whether introduced by Policy or Conqueſt, and a meer Uſurpation, till it be confirmed by the Repreſentatives of a Kingdom; and thoſe, Factions and Rebellions, that comply not with the motions of theſe; here onely excepting any ſuch Conſtitution, is a real de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of Chriſtian Religion, which is not the caſe now in hand.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>It is not impoſed by a lawfull Magiſtrate.</hi> Which leades me to the fourth inquiry, concerning this Government; which is compoſed of the Repreſentatives or Choiſe of the Kingdom, voting together in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation and determination of buſineſſes of State, and having an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon all Officers, Courts of Iudicature, without the aſſiſtance of King or Lords. Againſt which it is objected by ſome, that it is no Government. To which I anſwer, in the eſſential requiſites it is; though it cannot but be confeſt, by the diſtractions and parties that yet keep up theſe ſeverall factions, by the infancy of it in this Kingdome, it is not in all points ſo compoſed, as time and continued peace may order it. For we know, that of all the things imaginable, nothing meets with more difficulty, then the re-ſetling a Kingdome, that hath ſuffered ſome great mutation: 'Tis no ſmall paines that muſt reduce every No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to its right channel, ſilence all the clamours and complaints of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117721:7"/>men, refute the bold pretences and intruſions of others into Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And therefore one compared the alteration, yea, but the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Princes, to the removing of the world from one ſhoulder of <hi>Atlas</hi> to the other; in which time it is not imaginable, but the Earth muſt ſuffer a kind of Epilepſie, an Ague-fit, as it were; but much more, when the ſtrain of a Government is quite changed. I have ſaid enough to the lawfulneſſe of it in the former Concluſions, and chiefly now look upon the gaps in it, the eſcapes not yet mended; and compare them with what we enjoy, and conſider the Apologies may be made for what is wanting, with which we will begin. And thoſe we find chiefly to proceed from the Three great Challengers of an Intereſt in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to be oppoſed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe wholly addicted to Monarchy; againſt whom, though there hath been little need as yet of Medicinal phyſick, yet much of Prophylactick. I ſay, to prevent the deſigns of thoſe, whoſe judgments are wholly devote to Monarchy, and its utmoſt exactions; are wholly for the Prerogative-Royal; and the hard yoke ſo much groan'd under by others, is to them like an ornament; who think the little finger of this Government, thicker then the loins of the former; the grievances of the former, whips; the laſhes of the latter, ſcorpions. Now from ſuch judgments, what can be expected but ſuitable practiſes and plots, to return things to the ancient Model; and they have this to encourage them in their hopes (which cals for the greateſt prudence of the preſent Authority) The votes of all other Monarchs, whoſe intereſts muſt needs joyn with the full glory of Monarchy, though probably other inferior ends may a little rebate the edge of their deſires this way. But who would not fear ſuch a ſtorm? and can this be any other then a <hi>remora</hi> to the full and free eſtabliſhment of affaires?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Party in the Kingdom, who would moderate, but not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Monarchy; they were for the Government, but not the extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, nor full cariere of it; and I muſt ingeniouſly confeſſe, it ſeems a very excellent Form, as might be made out, if it were ſeaſonable; onely thus excepted; It was not approved of by the Supreme Power of the Nation. Now the ſatisfying in ſome things, and reſtraining in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers this Party, cannot but have ſome time impeded a full ſettlement; for the care that muſt eye every appearance of danger, could not but a while attend this, which had not only a Chymera of fear in it; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, that not onely a great part of the Kingdom, yea, and of the beſt part too, the Miniſtery, who have the advantage of the Pulpit; many of the Nobility, who have great trains of dependents, yea moſt of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117721:7"/>Gentry, and the whole Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> are engaged as partiſans in it, and very probably the whole body of Royaliſts complying at leaſt with the opportunity of their action.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>Hydra</hi> of confuſion, the motley hundred-headed Faction of the <hi>Levellers,</hi> like a Torrent threatning to carry all before them, who created two troubles this laſt yeare to the Government on foot: On which a very diligent eye, and a ſtrait bit is neceſſary; for it being an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, that is entertained in the dregges of the people, and baſeſt ſort of men, and deriv'd to them from ſome that have the power of the ſword, and others the knack of committing powder-plots to paper, baited with very plauſible inſinuations, is like to carry high, if once well on motion; and though it hath had ſome diſcouragements, yet doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe takes up the moſt ſerious thoughts of our Senators, leſt it prevaile above them. For of all that I have yet nam'd, I confeſſe, in my thoughts, this bids faireſt for a Supremacy, I wiſh I may be ſo well deceived for though I believe it is look'd upon as a meere bubble or trifle, that muſt needs be its owne ruine; yet if well ſcann'd, it will prove a very poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Conſtitution, though a moſt Atheiſticall one. 'Tis true, the hang-byes of it, I meane, the furious Vulgar, conceive of it as a thing of ſuch a nature, that would never endure, yet as it is contriv'd and plotted by the great Engineers and movers of it, is farre another thing. Ile adde,</p>
            <p n="4">4. The proſecution of the warre in <hi>Ireland,</hi> a neceſſary Expedition for the Engliſh ſafety, hath ſtood in the way of other diſpatches. A ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice which hath been hitherto proſperous to amazement, and may well juſtifie the care of it, by its ſucceſſe; wherewith the undertakers and abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of it are ſufficiently rewarded: beſides, the ſafety and ſecurity hath ſmil'd on <hi>England,</hi> by the removall of that danger, and hath ſhut up the way againſt the invading feare of Invaſion. Now all theſe laid toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may apologize for greater defects, than we can object againſt the preſent Government, as will appeare if we look upon them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Ile begin with the greateſt firſt, and that is, The not effectual ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Learning and Religion; for Learning is the Onely ordinary means for the promotion of Religion. And here, O ye Worthies! let me ſpeak in the behalfe of this great pillar of States, without which they crumble into confuſion, and ſinke into Barbariſme; Religion leaves that Kingdome ſuddenly, that is not pav'd and adorn'd with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117721:8"/>Learning. Tell me, what hath reduc'd this face of thing, into ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a forme, that mean Proficients now excell many great Names, that were on the wing in former times, but Learning? ſhou'd we remember the Popery and Superſtition of former times; let us remember the want of Learning: And can we hope that Religion ſhould ſtand firme, when this is diſcountenanc'd? Lord, let us never ſee the reſult of ſuch a depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture! Religion is ſtill unſetled, and 'twere worth our moſt earneſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that we might ſee it compoſed, and the Government of the Church ſtrongly confirm'd. And what more effectuall meanes, then the ſetling of a competent meanes for the Miniſtry, and Univerſities of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, thoſe ſprings that make glad the City of God. But let us conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in compariſon with this, the Eſſentials of both theſe yet maintain'd and upheld, and the gracious offertures for the promotion of them in the circumſtantials; and I wiſh the further proſecution of it may be the ſerious care of thoſe that ſit at the Helme. Government is neceſſary to Religion, and Religion eſſentiall to good Governments and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all States have joyn'd theſe, in die cementing themſelves, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all into a body.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Taxes and burdenſome Impoſitions, that ſo pinch mens ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, are great arguments and complaints againſt this Government. But let us conſider the neceſſity of them; Can an Army be maintain'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe? can the great charges and expences be defrayed without them? and can the ſtate of things be held up in any tolerable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without the help of Armies? Did we not cry out upon former Taxations and Subſidies; and will we not be content with temporary exactions, to be freed from ſtanding ones? But what, ſay ſome, is become of thoſe great ſums, that Royal Lands and Spiritual Manours have brought in? I anſwer, Shall we put in truſt our ſelves, and ſtatus, and not relye upon the faithfulneſſe of the intruſted? We may with more equity, if we conſider all things, wonder at the fewneſſe and lightneſſe of ſuch exactions, then quarrel at the ſuperfluity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The perpetuity of the Parliament, and too long Power of the Repreſentatives. But let us conſider, whether it be for our ſecurity, that in this flux of things, and the ſtorm that is in the world, the Great Balaſters of it ſhould give up their hold, and leave affairs to that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn hope, that neceſſarily will enſue upon ſuch an <hi>inter-regnum,</hi> as it were: Theſe things are to be done by degrees, and inſenſibly, when bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117721:8"/>are nearer a full and happy accommodation. Rather let us bleſſe our ſelves in that Order and Hope we ſit under, by the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and prudence of thoſe faithful Steerers, that have ſtood up for our ſafety, that have ventur'd and hazarded their all for us, and who are daily conſulting a further ſettlement and aſſurance of our hopes. And thus far I dare promiſe my ſelf, that every day will give us greater encouragements, till our deſires arrive to a kinde of <hi>non ultra.</hi> I have now performed the task I ſet my ſelf; if it may gain its end, I ſhall think my ſelf well rewarded; However, it cannot but remove prejudice, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept wilfully and cauſeleſſely retain'd.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
